forward to this computer all right
welcome to my computer screen
hello everyone um i will just i'll just
say a few words about myself yeah please
i'm i'm daniel i'm in in austria
um yeah for those of you that don't know
this is this little country that many
people think it
belongs to germany but
so it's it's it's a little mountain
country um
and i'm from vienna i'm studying
japanese studies um
and i'm very interested in the kyoto
school in haitica and nietzsche
in dostoyevsky in kalyan these are like
my
my favorite thinkers well that says a
lot about you right there
how did you get how did you get involved
in
in philosophy and reading jung and like
how long have you been doing that
quite long actually um
i think the first philosophy book i
picked up
was i mean already at high school
um yeah
mean i had i had some i had some phases
in my life where i didn't read
so much of philosophy but i already
always came back to it
um but
just just the the danger that this kind
like of
president in the world and now more so
than ever i think
especially in the last last few years
and i think it has become really
strong the whole you know what we call
the meaning crisis
in kind of the vivekan sense um
and but these these things stretch back
much longer into the you know into our
history right
yeah and for me it's just it's more like
i'm doing this out of necessity
trying to understand everything trying
to understand the nihilism of our time
yeah and also trying to to find
the ground
i don't i don't do that also like i had
some personal struggles
like most people who read philosophy
yeah
yeah there's nothing like crisis
yeah i mean i mean now we now we have
the sense of crisis and the word crisis
is all over the place right
yeah yeah yeah it's it's it's uh
it's not obvious what it is
right exactly
when they don't know what the crisis is
they're probably
not talking about what the crisis is
right it's it's
it's it's that strange of a of a time
it seems yeah we don't know what happens
we don't know what what
just happens when when this ground
breaks away
beneath us and we don't know why because
most people of us
don't have like this kind of like um
deep knowledge of history like people in
the 19th century sometimes
had yeah they could read greek they
could read latin
right and and now more and more people
don't have access to this world of the
past anymore
right even though it's strangely
it's strangely available right you can
get a youtube video on any
[Laughter]
any part of the history but there's some
way i think what you mean
my senses
like in the in the 19th century this
sense of history
was a different sense than we have now
it seems that that i mean it started
then out there because even nietzsche
criticizes
this kind of like false sense of his or
the for the first time sense of history
i mean johannes described this right
yeah that we have all become
antiquarians and this kind of
like historians book readers reactive
talents
yeah um and for nietzsche this was in
the unpublished notes that there's
something great
is is awakening with this historical
sense
right and we're kind of like departing
from
our history in a sense and then moving
into this era of progress where we try
to get away from it
and and declaring everything that has
been uh
rendering it meaningless yeah that that
which has been is now
it's not worth a fan it's not worth
anything right
right yeah totally
what's what had you get into japanese
studies
my no i was reading a lot of japan
novels from japanese offers and i was
also kind of like very interested in the
architecture and i i've known some
heidegger
then and i knew that heidegger was very
um i mean he's he's like he's like a
master for the japanese philosophers
they yeah
he's so much revered there and then
and this kind of like
and there's always this fascination for
all these traditional art forms in japan
um
and i think we can learn a lot from the
east
so i mean that's what's initiating is
outlining in the book how we can
how we can move through our own nihilism
right right with the help of
buddhism yeah it just says
so people are not familiar with who
nishitani is he's part of the
kyoto school right which is basically
the
you know when basically
it's a school of japanese philosophers
who
who really were oriented with with the
german philosophers
right the continental philosophers and
they've
they've you know you really see it's
you know you really see in my in my
experience of reading them so far which
hasn't been
that long um you really get the profile
they do it profoundly right in a very
very deep way
and especially this thing about about
the sense of nothing
or the sense of of sunyata or emptiness
and i think the thing i've
i've been appreciating is is just how we
kind of miss that one in the west
it's kind of like we
we just yeah we just we just kind of
missed it somehow and like
because we've missed it in some sense i
think this is what i'm appreciating
about this
you know nishitani in the book religion
is in
in nothingness is
the missing of which um
has nothing become a kind of absence
right a nullity or an uh like a nihilism
right
and and and that and in the east they
really have this sense of
of the of the kind of the existential
kind of womb that everything's in in
some sense right is this
is is the is the essence of
of their perceptions and how they see
and what and and so they have this very
inclusive
strong sense of emptiness um
and the consequence of
not seeing anything right like
has been huge um and i my sense with
heidegger i
is is it seems like especially
in heidegger's work around the the
pre-socratics
there's a sense in which it seems like i
i think from heidegger's perspective it
seems like
he thought it could have it could have
gone
more in the nothing way right
there was like it couldn't like there
was the possibility of that with
heraclitus and
and you know all the different
pre-socratics
you know so he's in some sense his going
back into history in the sense of a new
beginning i really kind of get this
sense
in a certain way in the atmosphere of
the
original philosophical thought right is
that
in some sense he's trying to he's trying
to think that through
right begin it again right and
you can you can you can really see a
very very deep
kinship i i'm imagining he doesn't talk
about it that explicitly but i'm
imagining a really deep kinship with
with taoism and buddhism
right in some way doesn't talk much
about
emptiness as a concept right he talks
about for example in the thing essay he
talks about how the jug
and what constitu what is constitutive
of the jug is the emptiness
yeah he says in german and
for example shunyata is also is
translated with the same word in in
german
it's kind of like this this emptiness as
fullness in that sense so when you have
like when you have like a glass that
this
is not nothing yeah in a sense but
there's this
fullness of this emptiness right
right and i i know i've
read uh late
from the later heidegger where he talks
about pamenitis
and he really i think he really wants to
trace back
this his this hit this oneness
to pamenides right
right and that you know the one of the
things that
um one of the things the back of my mind
is
is our four-way
dialogues is that that um i've been
doing with chris
and john and jordan
um the next one we're going to be doing
is going to be on
looking at
essentially what in dialogues right in
philosophical dialogue right what is it
what is it to to basically look at
the ground of it being emptiness
right in contrast to something where i
think most conversations
ground is more in like narrative right
and so so one of the things we want to
explore
right is this sense in which um
what you know what what is that
difference between
you know something coming from narrative
right which which john with his
his his work on religion and all that
kind of stuff he's i've been hearing him
talk a lot about that right which is
he kind of thinks that narrative is is
not his primary
right as as as many people assume that
it is
right um and that there's that there's
another way
to get at it right that's not that isn't
based in narrative that's based based on
some
something much more primordial right so
so there's
we're opening up this exploration in in
the sense of like well what is it
to have
a dialectic that goes into dialogues
from from emptiness right
revealing that emptiness displaying that
emptiness right
having it a rise in emptiness shot like
versus like narrative and going back and
forth
the thing i think what nishitani would
say to this is
because because history for us in the
west has always been this divine drama
right
starting from the fall of mankind
and then stretching back to the the s
cattle to the
the to the end of the world the
apocalypse
and for nishitani this would then be
like the historicity yeah
of things and maybe it's it's nishitani
i mean
knew german very well i think he even
received the go to medal and
also like one of the highest prices of
of
yeah for for for scholarship in germany
what you can receive
yeah um in in
[Music]
in german that's historicity means
something like there's there's something
sensed to you
so historicity has always been sent from
a trans-historical plane
which is like the divine yeah
historicity starts
from this trans-historical plane
yeah which we have always located
outside
right played the history of platonism
christianity is
always like a world beyond
this italian would call it like the the
the beyond
the store yet the on the shore like from
this shore like beyond right
okay and now what what he sees then is
in nature need to really struggle to
overcome this
but he couldn't find a place or a
standpoint where he could
we could re this like recharge
the historicity of history for him
for him things like the diagonalized the
dionysian
um were like pointing back to
two methods and
then you're then you're a narrative
again yeah
yeah so for him to be
fully in time to realize historicity
radically in time
[Music]
that would require the standpoint of
emptiness and then you can give
then you can give like a whole new
meaning to to
um what happens because now
now when i've thought of this because we
were talking
about progress right in the in the last
lecture with johannes
and now it's this kind of sense we are
in this
this linear um
kind of like phase of history where
the gold historicity has become
radically imminent nishitani would say
the same thing
historicity was imminent
it has it has it really imminent so that
means
we have like this line and all
everything that happens
yeah have is is like sucked into
this this progress thinking right right
right and we can't and then we can't
and everything that happens then we try
to think in that kind of like framework
yeah and even when we try to think
outside of that framework
we end up doing it in such a way that's
in that framework it's so there's so
much gravity to it
yeah yeah so and the standpoint of
emptiness then
would mean that we shackle ourselves
from that
and then we can we can we can realize
time and history again right in their
in their historicity which is
this very primordial historicity yeah
well but but we probably won't make as
much money though
[Laughter]
there's something about like when you
said that like i really appreciated the
thing that
you know you said about you know that
this this
yeah there's a there's a sense in which
this
sense of progress this linear sense of
history we project it out in the future
we project it out of the past we orient
it based on
it it's and it's got this kind of
forward momentum that
seems to be like faster and faster and
faster and faster and faster and you're
right it's
i'm in silicon valley right i'm in you
know the bay area and this is
the the highest concentration of like
straight line historicity right
you can kind of feel it like you know
this everything is about that
streamlining it right
and of course i think this really gets
into heidegger's sense
of gestel and um
you know the age of technology all of
that seems to be really
dancing together with this
but the thing you said about like
that first thing you said what was it
trent when you said the thing about
trans something trans history starts
always beyond the door right
yeah and that is that's not this
that's not the straight line that sense
of history right
there's still elements of it because we
still believe in salvation
by technology but most people do
right and and and i i once said this in
in another conversation i think i said
like before we had like the overlords of
like
like the church for example and now we
want to to get into the machine of the
overlords of silicon valley
where they upload us to to like the
clouds and there we can like i don't
know
live in eternal hellos
yeah totally totally so the thing he's
saying about
so for from your from your vantage point
how does like how does one
allow or realize this sense of emptiness
that the realization of such
as you said like breaks the shackles
right
out of this sense
what is the what's the tech the talos of
that like how
like what do you get is the sensibility
that
how does that happen
i would say the following when we
maybe maybe doing like this the shitani
maybe would construct the argument
something like this so we have imminent
history in this on this line right
that means we have kind of like
what what heidegger would call the will
to will right
we will we will every activity for its
sake
so so nishitani says in the book um
religion nothingness he says
um um
what happened after death of god is that
all facets of human life have been
have have sort of like it seems as they
are permeated by this thrill to will
what he calls an autotellic will
so they are goals in themselves they
have
no higher goal beyond themselves yeah so
you have it's you you have sex for the
sake of having sex
you have pleasure for the sake of having
pleasure right
you build you build you build houses for
the sake of building
houses yeah which is kind of less than
the like
expanse of this kind of like bubble
right which some some countries had i
think in the u.s you also had this kind
of like housing bubble
disclosed however is this i mean he says
this is this heat
of modernity this is what johannes would
call it the explosion of modernity right
yeah and what is what for nishitani what
is this close this kind of like this
infinite drive
beyond everything humans do
yeah and the buddhists and i would also
say the christians
have identified that with
karma or sin
and and karma is this notion of
it seems that you you always you always
have to do something
yeah you always have this burden on you
on your shoulders that you have to do
something right um but
because we can realize that we we still
have
like we have freedom ahead of us in a
sense
we we we kind of like we can make
ethical conclusions and that's that's
coming to the senko
one of kill the buddha on on the road
when you see him
yeah that means when you see an idol for
example when you see
let's say you see i don't know an
ex-girlfriend
you really liked but she doesn't want to
know anything but you still keep
you with your infinite drive you still
keep texting her right
and then but that that causes suffering
right
to you and and your your ex-girlfriend
but then you realize it and you you
you're letting go
in this glass in height sense yeah
active letting go of that
idol and then then you you come
closer to yourself right and then that
closer to yourself
right that sense of coming close to
yourself in some sense is
getting closer to in some sense getting
closer it's like a little hit of nothing
like some kind of releasement like it
realizes a sense of
of a space or something that opens up
right
like at least that's for me whenever i
like notice i'm in some
neurotic loop or something like that and
all of a sudden i'm like oh
like i'm crazy there is there's like a
little moment of like where i see
what i was seeing with right i see my
own drivenness
and there's like a little like a
disidentification of some kind and some
kind of a stasis
or a spaciousness that opens up
and i'm wondering if that's if that's
what you know nishitani is kind of
getting at
right about like is that like a little
taste of maybe something like
emptiness or something like the nothing
i mean remember i mean
[Laughter]
that's a funny story by the way about
this about the nothing um
kind of like an x-chorus um when
heidegger gave a talk about the nothing
so being in nothing in the late 20s
um he said that a talk in the 70s
very late late talk of his he said that
there was a japanese student there who
immediately understood
what he wanted to say and he translated
the
the um this lecture
into japanese yeah and the japanese
immediately understood that this
this this knee kill this nothing is not
shall not be understood in a in a
nihilistic way yeah but all the
europeans
did totally
well it's kind of that that you know
there's
there's so many ways that that just
makes sense right
it does it does seem to me
one of the things that i think what
you know i mean all around me
you just go to a suburb right in these
kind of
track homes and these shopping malls
in the in the senior citizen parks and
like there's something they're almost
like um
the not like the the nihilism like
bleeds out of them
right but they're all these kind of
spectacles in some way
right that um
they're obviously pretending to be
something
right like the houses are built to look
like houses
such a strange thing you know when you
think about but america's got a lot of
that going on
like big time um and right underneath
the surface
if you really like it at least in my
experiences like when you really feel
into it
right the parking lots and like
you know the shallow conversations and
and also just the fact that nobody's
walking around going
like this is absolute hell
right there's you can at least for me i
can like sense this kind of
hollow queasiness right that like
it goes right down it's like a dropping
sensation in my solar plexus it's like
not like kind of nauseating but it's got
that
nullity right that that sense of absence
of meaning essentially right
it's i mean it's these hollow isles
right when you walk through for a
large city today and you you're like you
have this explosion of sounds
images and smells and and people
and and traffic and and and
everything and and it's just it's just
this
kind of like but they're all hollow
right
in a way these images are all hollow
when you when you
come with your nietzsche and hammer and
hammer on your idols
it's they they break immediately yeah
yeah there's no there's no substance
behind all these things and then that's
that's nihilism when you when you when
you lose your substance
i mean that's that's a collapse i mean
for this eternity that this
he has these three levels of three
stages
where substance thinking and when then
that collapses you have nihilism
yeah yeah
and then and then underneath that is
sunyata
exactly exactly because that's what he
was saying about
nietzsche right he said he's like
nietzsche didn't go far enough
into the nihilism he stopped too short
he's like no you should go into it
further
i mean he said something a lot as he
said something like um
he he he came closest to the standpoint
of buddhism
than all thinkers before him but
he couldn't come to this final place
that's the tragedy of nietzsche right
in this final place
what what is like if we
if one comes to this final place this
sanyata
and then i go and i walk i take a walk
and i
walk in like the house you know the
houses of hell
and suburbs and the temples of nihilism
and i've i've said yes to the great
doubt
right i've like and i've
i've realized this sense of i've gone
all the way through
and and i'm
i'm in zenyatta and then i walk
through the suburb and then i go to
disneyland and i do these things
what what what is the difference
i think
i think it's hard to say i mean
even even when we talk okay i'm not
enlightened
so i can't say anything about that
but it seems to me that that
you will still feel the heat
enlightenment is not something it's
often not
something that is like constant
i mean often you only have glimpses of
enlightenment and that's often what
in buddhism actually these are these
glimpses
that lead you to the journey and keep
you there
yeah and it's often what you would you
said before when you
for example when you're really neurotic
and i think many many buddhists
also had the same great doubt right they
really went through a period of
suffering
of anxiety of nihilism and then at one
point you start
doubting that is that really me who is
having all these thoughts who who is
that
is having these faults
and and if you can if you can release
that if you don't get attached to to it
if you can find momentary releasement of
it you can maybe find some greater
more aspirational forces right
right and that's then what in this
religious sense this higher self right
second self the self with capital s in
the jungian terms
right right
but because you asked me i can show you
yeah
so that's john wiki also recommended it
it's the this kyoto oh yeah
intro in through book so do you have it
uh yeah i have it on pdf
so when we have we have these 10 oxford
pictures right that you may be familiar
with
um
here so so
and and we could say this is like a
quest to the higher self
in a way yeah so so
what it what it says is it just like you
good guy no
[Laughter]
what do you mean you're not like that
looks just like you
so so in some sense at first
you you you're wondering you have kind
of like a sense of
awe in the world yeah and but still
you feel if something is missing
and then you see the ox and you just see
the back of the ox
first so you see like glimpses of the
higher self
and then then you're fighting with the
ox because like the higher self
it's it's like when when nietzsche
described what sargeras
went when he had the great the heaviest
fault
in in in the swiss alps right
um he has this sense of there isn't
doesn't he has to to go down
he has this underground of god he has to
to um
throw away his his present ego
and and move in this direction of of
sagatustra his higher self in that sense
um that's a fight that's always like a
fight
and then you discipline it and that's
that's a hard practice in a sense that's
like the hard meditation retreats
but days and days and and it's pain
and and all of that which arises
and then and then number six would then
be
playing with the orcs right you have
mastered
it you're not a master of yourself and
you can you can that's like i would say
that's like
also like the childlike elements if you
can
come back can can shine forth again from
your being
right right
and then then he the last
the last two are these so it's this
and this and i've read that it's not a
succession of
those but a constant repetition of those
two
emptiness yeah and
the rolling of the world just
pure beauty of the world
and you can see that then again you
don't you don't have to
you don't have to like when you see like
three or so you don't wanna like
you don't wanna um
what distort the being of the tree
or you don't it's also not that you just
go on your on your
street where you live and you you just
you just don't recognize it
because that's what most people do right
when you're in nihilism you just you're
just
obsessed with yourself yeah
yeah and you don't pay you don't give
any value to any outside things
the birds the trees right the the
the sparkling of the water something
like this
this is kind of like you're in like that
in that in nihilism is kind of like
you're the most
you're always haunted by your own sense
of
substantiality right and it's such a
claim
and has needs and you have to take it
for walks and you gotta like make sure
it's liked and like
but there is this kind of sense right
where
where it it's it's
i think it's hard it's hard to it's hard
to comprehend
to what degree
how deeply unsubstantial the self is
right
however it's very
the very not the very um
unsubstantiality of it
allows for right this
the mistake of itself as substance
right it's it's like it's a
i mean if you just well have you ever
done have you ever done any of the
meditation retreats
have you gone for long since before very
short very short like two days
three days something
for very um i would say
believers of of like christian um
um faith so often the translator of
religion
or nothingness he he wrote once a piece
where he said there was one
one koan um nishitani was particularly
fond of um
and that was the following um
so he said
and these are really paradoxical
questions right so he says
and when when paul says in the in the
in the letter to the galatus i think
um that's i'm taking that very seriously
as a sen
buddhist says nishitami i think i can
understand it and then he says
so paul paul says i live but not
me christ lives in me
not paul lives not he himself lives
and then nishitani asks who is
speaking there
okay
no i i have not the german version of
this book um
so i will you have to translate yeah
no no it's not but these kind of like a
talk
translations of me are so bad
um okay
okay paul says i live
but not me lives christ lives in me
so not paul does not paul lives
not he himself lives and the shitani is
asking
who's speaking there yeah
when when christ lives in me yeah
is that so that would be like the
obvious question
is paul asking is paul speaking or is
christ speaking
right
and for deep believers this is this can
really haunt you
yeah yeah um
and but there's like when when you're in
deep nihilism
and you say oh the world is all bad and
then so
who's speaking there yeah
yeah yeah
and you know often often then a few
moments later you're like just you you
can
you can have half moments of awe and
wander again
you're just you're just like you feel
like as you're normal
but what what you see is that there's
this kind of like
what he wants to get you s there's this
kind of like non-substantiality to you
and you often don't even know who's
speaking in you
that's often these kind of like when we
talk in the jungian way the shadow
realization when you have this like
sometimes when you feel when you're
really in a bad place you have this all
these
very disturbing thoughts and maybe
resentful thoughts
and then you say but who's speaking
there
that's what what you might ask yourself
yeah totally totally
so who's speaking there
i mean they could only intellectually
that's usually not what you do with a
koan
to try to intellectually explain it
but but even even here that the the
german
and um she
this german scholar who who wrote this
said
i wrote um that
sort of aston martin which means
um that our language drops
out of out of kind of like
like we are stunned by this question
and then he says maybe in these
blinks of an eye without words the
the authentic dialogue and its long
shared way to understanding a
realization begins
oh great great
i know this with like people in the west
always want to understand
everything yeah and nishitani and
the saint koans really tried to like get
you out of this
framework yeah not it's not about
understanding
that's why they also paradoxical you
can't
you can't understand them with your
logic but it's about it's about
getting to a deeper place and then about
participating
in the world realizing yourself nature
your buddha nature
and thus having a deeper participation
within the world
right right i right
it's like a part of i mean
whenever i've had like like kind of
shifts like of insight of some kind
right um
like big or small like there is always
this experience of yeah it is
the same thing right
looks reveals itself differently right
in that in that way something speaks
that on some level
right in the shift
i see it right
and then i recall that i've on some
level
always seen it but haven't seen it right
but now it's obvious
right this kind of sense
of kind of this disclosure and i think
that's
i mean essentially that's why i think
i'm on a personal level why i
why like i'm i i grapple with the with
the
the text that i do and everything is
because on some level it's like it's all
about that right
about on some level um
because it seems to me that philosophy
or i could say like them
you could say if there's such a thing as
like a measure right of
of getting it right or seeing it is
is is i've always noticed my perceptions
change
right like it's a perceptual thing it's
like that the world shows up
and something shines forward more right
and there's
there's that sense right and i think
it's one of the things we were talking
about earlier like my like my experience
of reading heidegger and being in time
it's really that like that's that sense
of
you know on some level he's i think
heidegger is a little bit co-annie
right um sure
with that quality of like having you
step so far outside of your frame of
reference
to then look and see if you can
look where where he's asking you to look
right and just that gesture right
i would imagine is something similar in
a in a koan
right is cohen
seemed to be like that like i always got
this since coans were designed to
frustrate the out of you
right look at this
give you a go ahead and go sit
underneath the rock and like
eight years like you're in knots you
know and the master comes up and he's
like
you ready yet and it gives the answer
and it's like nope 10 more years
but there's a kind of a moment of like
that struggle
there's a transcendence in that struggle
right
yeah but that's when you read heidegger
i mean first of all it's just what does
he want from me
yeah what does this all mean yeah
and then you you struggle with the text
and and sooner or later
your what you just said your perception
of the world will will
change will alter yeah yeah
for the place where where you
that you can see how how being
reveals itself to you in a way
and when i watched some of your videos i
i kind of like i had the
when you were walking around the street
right and and
i've had the sense that you're really
then
they're getting at what heidige wanted
you to notice
yeah yeah definitely
yeah but he won't give me a straight
answer if i got it or not
[Laughter]
yeah that that quality of being you know
of the world well i guess the thing i
just
you know i was going to ask you about
this too is
and i think we talked about this in
johannes's class a bit
um but then we the time was up um
this connection between elite alethea
right the event like the event of
wells evo
degeneres like translation this
abscondedness
right or concealment um
and
what and and this is part this is really
where i've where i've really learned
this is in
in circling what we do is encircling
right which is just
it's a kind of a relational it's like
being in relationship
and being with what is and and
and if it's interesting to think about
like well if if if a practice
being with that which is right is a
practice
right the only way it could be an
aspiration is if in some way
is can is concealed right because the
more
is the only way it i have a feeling on
some level i was like i think
circling ended up um accidentally being
addressing nihilism in that way right
because it kind of calls forth a
different
stand right
anything right and especially with each
other it's very difficult to do with
people on an interpersonal level like
just be with what is
like there's so many different pulls of
social norms and everything so
like to really have people practice
like not fixing anybody right not
helping anybody but just being
in the presence of and
that there's that there's that there is
something here and that
and that it's most likely it's deeper
truth
is hidden however there's a sense in
which if we can
hear that which i sense
is concealed which is an interesting
thing is like what
what the hell are you perceiving
actually when you sense some things
hidden
right in what way is it present
and i'm and i i think that there's i
want to tease that out a little bit if
we can like
in in your opinion about like this sense
of concealment
right um and that sense of emptiness and
nothing
right because it's it is really
difficult to to really think about
nothing because i keep wanting to
and as i'm reading nishitani i'm getting
i think i'm starting to
gr i'm starting to grok it on like the
corner of my
eye for a second or two before it slips
away
but but i keep wanting to go think about
nothing and i get this picture of like a
thing that's not
nothing right i don't get the sense that
that's what he's talking about
like there's an absolute nothing right
it's it even negates itself right it is
its own
negation right it's like it allows for
but it it it's very difficult you can't
it's like any kind of representation
you can't directly it seems to me you
can't directly represent it it can't be
represented
it'll just negate all of your
representations or something
um but this connection between
feeling into what's hidden and then also
being present to the emptiness
it seems like those things are very very
connected
do you agree
because it's inexhaustible yeah
this this these mysteries
that that you can uncover
unreal they are in
inexhaustible yeah this was always
our attempt to make everything
representational
fixed exhaustible
consummate that brought them to collapse
well if we can allow for this
possibility
of things unfolding themselves
into an inexhaustible mourners
if we allow thing if
we genuinely allow things to be like
that
in this kind of like we we we are
releasing them we are liberating them
for from our
you know from this kind of like i mean i
had a god talks about this
of fix it positive
this kind of like you know
it comes from also foreign which is
putting forth
when you put this forth you you pause it
yeah then it can't
it can't change anymore it's fixed in
that sense
and we try to make this with everything
right that's why it's
gay stella it's the gathering of
position
um and when we do that
we we we we are
we make a thing and make it an object
something radically graspable in that
sense
for us for our intellect
but we we do not we
um rob um uh things
to to have their own
mode of presencing to have their
their inexhaustible mourners behind them
um yeah in emptiness
is pure olive fear it's a thing
yeah it's late bear
yeah you see it in its pureness
you can see you can see a tree and then
nishitani uses i mean he has three
um okay here's these three levels
i think you know this field of
consciousness
he says it in japanese substance
thinking
you you conceive of things as substance
then you have field of nihilism
caused as should i you see
things just from your own perspective in
a sense from your your
your subjective stance and then you have
field of shunyata which we call things
are
jitai which is things
in themselves as themselves you can see
a tree as it is
as a tree and it's it's
pure in its pure in its yeah in its pure
being
yeah yeah
and you you you're so to see you've
thrown all your
your shells off so to say
yeah and for nishitani it's also maybe
worth clarifying for him it was always
nihilism is a place we have arrived at
through our thinking so to say and it's
it's we have to go back to the what he
called the near side so the truth is on
it's on the it's on the nearer side then
you are self
near to you so to say that's what that's
what he says in the book
it's this absolute near side where we
have to step
back towards yeah
and then that's why he uses in the book
this kind of like
dropped off body mind this sent metaphor
from dogen
yeah so you you throw off your your
representations
your conceptualizations your frames
you throw all of that off and you see
just
pure pure being
yeah and that's that's i would say
that's pure alephia as well so he
sometimes
draws connection with alephia yeah that
makes a lot of sense
it's it's interesting you know there's
like uh
and you can notice there is a sense in
which like with
with sound right
there's a there is a way in which you
can actually really hear the silence
in it right it's a little bit it's a
little bit more difficult
with seeing
but there is a way we're even seeing
there's a
there's some there's some way in which
what is that detect this time goes
through that whole dialectic
about the eye
where he talks about was it the eye it's
the eye um
sees but it's also
precisely in it not seeing itself
right like there's that sense where it
negates itself
and so it's like it's not it's it's it's
emptiness
right it's it's not seeing
is present saturates all the seeing
right and there is this kind of sense
where
if you look if you just look at the most
simplest perception there is a sense
where you can kind of feel almost like
it's like a
you can in some way see the mirror
right when you're looking in the mirror
right like if
if you look for the mirror like the the
the instinct is to look for
as if you it like as if the mirror
can reflect itself but it's the mirror
is the thing that's actually it's
it's um it's so revealed
it's concealed it conceals itself and
it's revealing of everything else
so there's this kind of quality of this
like because i think about this one
a lot of like well what is it to see the
mirror because on one level
the mirror when you look in the mirror
it's the only thing going on it's the f
it's the mirror
but the mirror is the one thing that
can't be reflected
right so to be present
to the only thing that's going on in
some sense right
requires a a kind of i don't know it
requires a letting
a letting happen right in that
in that degree
you have you have to kind of like
come back to your silence example to let
the silence
speak forth it's it's it's
so to say yeah by the way that's
interesting
maybe you'll notice um john i think john
cage that there's this
music piece four minutes 33 seconds
where the the the pianist it's just
open like sitting in front of the piano
and then doing nothing
oh yeah yeah totally it's just it's just
silenced
yes and i think he was exp
he was inspired by eckhart a little bit
in
con coming up with that that piece of
music
and you just you just have to think
about how how difficult it
is for people to bear these
four minutes 33 seconds and how how
difficult it
is to kind of like have
to do to like speak in nishitani
language listening of non-listening so
that we can allow for this we can allow
for this
we don't try to listen act like actively
and
then and try to like fixate something
make a representation again
and we also do not most people might
have eerie faults while this because we
we
that's what most people say when they do
meditation for the first time it's like
you can't you can't bear the
soundlessness
and just just doing nothing just just
releasing
everything you can't just you cannot
bear it
yeah yeah um
but just just letting the silence be the
silence
that's and that's so difficult right
right but there there is something there
that's that's the real thing
yeah it's it's not it's not nothing it's
in that sense it's
it's empty there's a there's an
if there's an empty yet but yet full
quality to it if you really allow it
to be there
it's funny as we're talking about it i'm
like
i feel like we're talking ourselves into
it
like like like i said this moment where
i felt like like my whole
my all my molecules like it did they
just went
they just got a little bit farther apart
for a second
like a little just the sense of space
yeah because isn't there it seems to me
that there's
like that sense of silence right which
in some ways
is is the clearing of sound right
in some in some sense it's like silence
well isn't it i mean isn't it like
technically true
like a composer what they're actually
composing is the silent
note like that's the thing that they're
conditioning
right it's they're not it's not the
sound
that they're actually um they are making
but in another level what the the
the music hey it's so hard to talk about
music
[Laughter]
but like um i think it was yo-yo ma who
talked about this it's like
you know on some level all he's doing is
conditioning a silence
like that's all like the whole song is
about
it's about conditioning the silence
right and so i
how i hear that is like that the music
is this
way of articulating that silence
in some way
i think that's why music is so
meaningful to us
as well if you think about the
like okay there's this
concert and then
there's this tension all the time you
play with the tension
right and and
behind that is this silence which which
kind of
it's this supportive background that
it's always
kind of maintaining all of that bringing
it into being
it's it's that's why i think nishita
talks about
the nothing as something like the
midwife of being
something like it it brings everything
it
everything is with with emptiness
everything is can only be with emptiness
and we have to have
an entrusting relationship with that
and but if we if we once have kind of
like
we know that it's there and
the silence i mean i think beethoven
lost
his his ability to hear right so he was
composing thief
um most many of his later works at least
um so
yeah and then
so there's this yeah there's this
fullness of silence
you can trust him yeah
i would say so yeah even then when it it
ends and then there's
and there's just this pure releasement
and and
and then out of this silence again is
like the people applauding
cheering
but but everything is only with the
silence
that that's i think the important thing
for me
everything can only be out of this
silence
every sound can only be out of the sense
otherwise it would it would just be
meaningless
if you just have sounds all the time
it's it's it will be
hell right yeah yeah there's this
consolation to silence
in a way yeah
trust trusting it
this is true i'm i i heard that's still
lingering
that's what we have unlearned in a way
just trusting
trusting the world in the sense it's i
mean that that's this critique
because we always try to plan and model
and and control
everything by our subjective will
but we can't trust the world anymore
that's so
interesting when you say that yeah
i said i wanna hang with that for a
moment
trusting the world
and and in how i'm hearing that
no pun intended but how i'm hearing that
um
is uh
is like trusting the silence of the
world
right perhaps that's
like well as i kind of step in that for
a second it's like there's
if i trust the silence listen for the
silence and then trust it
there's there is a sense in which that
which the world
can reveal it seems like
there's yeah there's like almost a
in that trusting relationship with
silence i
trust and then it speaks the world can
speak
right that which i would trust
is
speaks trustworthy and i i
like i really i just i just appreciate
it i was really beautiful
um
and also this sense of one of the things
i you know we always talk about how
up the world is right
like especially right now it's like just
have a fee like you just have a field
day
but it there's um but one of the things
i've noticed is that there's
uh that there's a there is a there's
actually an
uh a certain kind of ecstaticness
right in actually
seeing more of what's going on
and it's like the content
can be atrocious but there is a
sense in which that it that whatever the
truthness of it
right um
there is an ecstaticness to that truth
for me
right that somehow allows
actually like now that you say it yeah
there is a trusting quality
right to the world i never thought about
trusting the world
it's interesting but i think you're but
i think
you're onto something there
but that's when you have i think when i
think of it now is
just when you want to enter
into deep participation with someone
that
say trust is like that whole thing that
sustains you in a sense
without trust you can't trust is also
for societies societies where you have
people that can trust each other
interpersonally
these are societies that will flourish
but you can't you can't measure the
trust right
no no
yeah there's there is it ecstatically it
ecstatically arises when when
when things are as they ought to be
and
i'm just i'm just i'm just feeling
there's kind of the dialectic
right between when things are as they're
they ought to be i trust but then
there's this way in which
i trust and the world discloses
as it ought to be right
you're exactly yeah like
that that the world can disclose
in a trustful clearing if you will
right and it and that that could even be
the case
even at the shopping mall
with the nihilism oozing out right like
to real and i think this is what
heidegger
in in his work in the 30s especially
right the
you know the contributions they're
really like uh almost
it's almost written in code of some kind
right they're very difficult to break
into
but but all that stuff where he talks
about the abandonment of being
right beings withdrawal right and
and that to be with i think this is what
at least what he was saying in the 30s
my understanding is that to be with not
like
to be with nihilism was essentially
about
to to to be with
being as withdrawn right the being of
beings
but precisely is to tolerate
you know the experience of
it's it's total concealment right
without flinching i think that's
basically the challenge
that was the challenge like turn towards
it
realize your utter out of controlness of
the la the loss of it and but
that is that is being
it's being as forgotten
right and sticking with that and hanging
with that
and i'm i'm i'm getting this kind of
trusting relationship to this because
that's one of the things i noticed when
i was
you know i was talking about this um you
know when i
uh down in florida these retirement
communities that are just real
they're really they're strikingly
they're kind of simulations right when
you think about where
well it's like where you go to die it's
like it's so it's just really it's
it's really something but i i i did
notice
um a sense of getting
really interested in it and just seeing
it and like
seeing like doing my best just to
look right at it right in a kind of
openness and i it's interesting i think
yeah i think now that i think about this
i appreciate this there was a sense in
which
that took that was me on some level
trusting the world
and there was something releaseful
ecstatic about being in hell
right
that's i think what i'm getting from
what you're saying
so how do you feel about these
simulations
that that we we i mean heidegger would
call this something like
um regions of
i don't know representationality also
that we are constantly
into in our modern age so he saw this
coming with the tv
so you're always drawn out
into realms of of imagining
where or representation where you
that are not real similar simulations
and i mean for him this was a great
danger
because he saw this thing coming back
with us
technology um confusing our being
distorting our being um
and that's that's often that's often
what i feel and
also when i just heard you talking
you you you live in this it's kind of
like
we create these simulations for
ourselves to console ourselves
in a weird way um
and and then with the elderly it's not
we can't we can't have
we can't we don't trust
this process of becoming old
don't we don't trust them anymore i mean
okay they are old
what do they have what they what do they
have to tell us
that that's how many people think today
and then we just come
with our subjective planning and okay we
plan now we build a like a
resort or so for them that they can live
and do whatever they want to do um watch
tv
all the time or play golf also
um this is this is this instrument this
instrumentalization of human beings in a
sense
that's also what i see with if young
parents what they often do
like your kid is your project your kid
becomes your project
and you put your own subjective desires
onto your kid
and don't let the kids be whatever
that is like the own nature of the kid
right
heaven forbid they're talented then you
just optimize the out of that
go take the classes make sure they're
you know this anxiety around this
preciousness
right so it's a very strange time
i i mean i think what i think about it
is that what you asked me
like what yeah
well at some level it's all i think
about
all the time right really it's not
actually that's not far from the truth
um
it's interesting i i
what one of the one of the things that's
that
because there's so much urgency that it
seems to elicit right
it seems that urgency
i notice has a lot of people
get into a very kind of problem-solving
kind of consciousness around it
right and i really don't have that sense
that that that
that the world is a problem right that
can be solved i i really just
that in fact in fact i think sometimes
that
that kind of manic like
it just seems it just seems almost it
seems to exemplify the very thing
right on some level um so i i
feel actually it's interesting this is i
think a little bit what you're pointing
out like
this trusting the world i feel a lot of
trust
that there is intelligibility like
like this is in some way this is the
understanding
of being forgetting itself right
and it you can you can start to feel the
outlines of it
and it's intelligible right
um
but i don't i don't think i i i
personally don't
it's not like i feel hopeful that they
don't think it's
something to be hopeful about or not i
think it's like they're i think it is
dangerous
i do think that i think everybody if you
really ask them
we're heading towards a cliff and there
is this sense in which
we're just going to go over the cliff
like technology we're going to make the
faster phone we're going to
whatever the whatever it is there is a
sense in which it
it it's not it's not just man
yeah i like the
understanding of being forgetting itself
but that's really what's happened that's
really what's happening in sen
did this what what heidegger said
technology
coming into our being into our essence
confusing us distracting us
and then we we are in this constant mode
of
forgetting yeah losing memory
of being yeah and that's that's so i
think for
for for johannes this is also like we
have this
i think john mcveigh calls it salty
right and johannes would say
in greek so it's this remembering
your being
that's so important and that's not
that's
that's what we can't do if we are stuck
on our
field of consciousness mode because we
always
try to create something out of us in a
purely subjective fashion
yeah and remembering this is
kind of like it comes back to this kind
of like this higher self
kind of like the ox metaphor what we had
before with the sen
the same buddhist always has this ox
this higher self
that he he he realizes at one point and
then his journey begins
this this journey of aspiration of life
i'm inspiring to become a better person
i'm aspiring to
towards myself i'm orientating myself
towards the goods
um and i have i trust
i try in a sense i trust this this whole
thing that it is good
i trust i trust this is like a decision
you have to make
i trust that being is good yeah and
what i'm doing is is will bring about
the good
and i think what's what's what's so so
awful in our age of nihilism is because
we can't see the ground
it's it's like everything collapses into
nothing
yeah or it's rendered meaningless
it's devoid of very thing um
so it's it's like i think axel said this
in the group discussion um
yesterday he said something like we we
can make winter and summer
through our technology possibly but then
they aren't
winter and summer anymore they have lost
their meaning
as as the winter and summer and so it's
with time
by trying trying to to structure
everything
and and being on time all the time
and then producing on time
but then time gets devoid of meaning and
the products get
devoid of their of their their
original quality yeah yeah and then they
at least just
it's just stuff it's just meaningless
things so yeah yeah
there's a sense in which i
if i look at i mean a lot of the i think
i sent you the
i sent you the um the chapter that i
wrote
and a lot of it is about this but i
think
one of the oops
you still there i just i just lost you
for a few seconds
yeah okay cool sweet um
it's i think
and where i think where i think there's
an opening if you will
right um is precisely in that
that there's suffering right that
that all this is going on and that
they're suffering
right the fact that they're suffering
i think discloses something that that
isn't a technological disclosure
i think it discloses one place gestel
can't reach or hasn't totally reached
and it's that it's
it's that like human beings
we are we are
we are primordial care and so
if we show up in a world and it's it it
doesn't have meaning
it's gonna it's devastating right it's
in that that's painful right that
meaninglessness
is almost intolerable and that we suffer
is itself meaningful so there's a
disclosure
in in that and i would say that for like
just on a personal level
i think circling is actually a response
to nihilism
um in a way that like looking at it in
retrospect now
and looking at what's been responding to
and i think it's precisely
well i tell you what i just don't think
we have
any idea like
the impact of what it means that we've
like basically made almost all
synchronistic communication
optional right like
that basically it it used to be
not even that long ago if you needed to
talk to somebody
like if you need to exchange information
you had at least use the phone
i think with all this iteration of of
social media and the internet and how
fast that's happened
um
on a little bit more of an antique level
like speaking more optically
um
if we say that we become who we are
in and through relationship right which
is
i think obviously true right like
it's like if kilik would say it's like
the human being is a
you know the tension between the
um the mystery of participation
and of individuation right and that
in some sense a relationship right
is a is an enactment of that very
tension
right like if there wasn't relationship
what would you participate in right so
it's like on some level that's how we
become who we are
well what happens where where all of a
sudden life
existence doesn't demand
much of that from you
right it's the kind i think it's to say
i i
draw the analogy between i think with
the industrial revolution
mechanism basically made
functioning like remove
movement from functioning you have to
move anymore
and then all of a sudden there's this
new understanding or concern called
physical fitness
which transformed our relationship to
our bodies and then there's gyms
and all this kind of stuff right i i
think something's going on
on a on a interpersonal level
in terms of relationship that we've
taken
like we can that we can we can connect
and exchange information without having
to relate
uncollapsing those two i think is
i think it has catastrophic impacts and
i think
circling right
i think people's drawn to circling is is
in some way
similar to the
draw like is similar to the same
sensibility of like why people go to
gyms
before there was just enough like there
was so much you know
just your day-to-day existence in order
to function you had to
talk to people right and now most of
that's optional
that's never happened before and we
agree yeah so so i think it's like so
so for me there's something about um
there may be an opportunity with that
right
if we if we have to start doing it on
purpose
what does that mean right we start to
have relationships like kind of on
purpose
right it's there's something strange
about it
but but like maybe if we did it on
purpose
it it can disclose something that's
actually you know could be something
quite extraordinary i think there's
hints of that in circling
i think the logos is really about that
right
these kind of conversations um
there's a huge hunger for these
conversations and no wonder
right no wonder because they're amazing
like you know we've gone to some spaces
and understandings that i'm sure i'll be
thinking about for
like
probably it's kind of like when i when i
read
like just the kyoto school
philosophy or or the
the ancient school in in athens
or or what heidegger built in in
freiburg
there's so many like people who
were hungering to learn thinking and
they were all pilgrimaging
to the freiburg so i didn't know this
but
um in in in in
japan they had this kind of like this
kind of like
did really call it pilgrimage to um
freiburg
so freiburg so it's still usually when
you go to a shrine
on a new year or so and they call this
with freiburg
so and and
what i what i didn't mean when we look
at these conversations online that have
emerged now
and they they have become stronger now
in the corona rivals
because we are we're all locked up quite
for
four months um there's this
what did you say this hunger and there's
this this kind of like
this kind of religious instinct to to
participate relate bind yourself to
something higher
yeah yeah and we and to share this with
other people
who feel the same fulfill in the same
way
and then then you have these strange
ways of of
coming together in it just just
because these these these networks just
evolve
in a very strange way yeah um
and and but but just what we can build
around that it
can be so powerful when you when you i
mean
just the school of athens and the kyoto
school about what
did the all the scholars that were in
the in the heideggerian tradition for
example
and just just when you read some of
these dialogues they're so beautiful
um and
yeah i feel caught i feel like i in some
sense i feel
like i'm constitute
like i'm constituted by
these conversations like throughout my
life
like i've just i've had mentors like
that have just taken me under their wing
and like
i've been really fortunate a lot in like
a lot of respects
um and so
so and then doing circling for
you know which is all about this it i
felt
i i just have so much
it's like the com discourse
right being with right might
might send right is
it is how it is the way the logos weaves
the intelligibility of the world right
is in is
is in discourse like how else would it
do it and it
and it can do it inauthentically deeply
but you can also do it authentically
right and i think that's the
conversation that i'm most interested in
you know
that that's why we have right there
logos
dialogue and again the the
word for logos in in japanese is koto
and kotobar is language so there's a
similarity there
and i mean for for heidegger as well
language was
was really that thing that put
that that was we could talk
we we are the humans that have language
we we are
the animals that have language
and by through that we we can have we
can have a relationship with being
we have we have what did you say uh
the fullness of world so to say we have
rolled access
um through language
um
and then to me it's also
you evoked few few months ago when you
talked with
with um talked about
um the the fire
you know you're you're sitting around
the fire oh yeah the
logo yeah yeah yes and i i loved it i
love this image
so much because um it's not just
it it reminded me of the fiat the
four-fold of heidegger
because because it's like you know the
trees
that take up the take up the the the
the sunlight from the heavens and they
grow out of the
of the earth and then then you you
you you talk in in in earnestly
and then then you you're you're you're
sensing something divine the divine
logos
right right and then then
like then like the mortals and the
divine are also coming together
and that's this exemplification of the
fourfold
and what you can always see is like
what's surrounding you this darkness
i mean you're this little light right
okay you're sitting somewhere on a
i don't know like a prairie prairie or
something
and this you this little light and it's
all around you is this darkness
that's that's what i feel is this kind
of like but you you you haven't been
trust
if you have an entrusting relationship
to this darkness is
all that that surrounds you just
emptiness
yeah and then then and it's this
background and you
the little light that's foregrounded
i mean that's what the universe is is
this dark
totally this dark dark whatever
and we are this little light that that
is lighting on this
this this this black horizon
right that we don't understand and still
we and still we should trust it right
right still we should yes absolutely
going to be there's some way that that
trust in this conversation i really
appreciate this like
that trust in this
conversation hit me in a way in a new
way i'm
i'm looking forward to i'm looking
forward to how that works itself out i
can tell it's like
you know i don't know if you experience
this but like you know being a
conversation just something kind of
strikes
and then it wig it just you're out
walking around
and you don't even you're not even
conscious that you're like thinking
about it
and then all of a sudden you realize oh
you've been i'll be thinking about
anyways i'll be thinking about trust now
all week probably in between things so
i'll
i look forward to i look forward i'll
i'll keep
but you can you can when you have your
conversation about emptiness you can
noticed the trust between you
and and not just between the people
you're talking with
but also like like the whole
surrounding yeah and also trust in
in the in the in the divine logos so to
say
and how this how this brings forth new
new
insights and awe and wonder and the good
sort to say
and how people and and how how people
shine forth in a new way
and how you you you get closer to this
this
alephia so to say and trust this thing i
think
trust is what what drives this in a way
yeah it's definitely what gives access
to your heart
for sure yeah
it's interesting i i and i have to i
have to have to bring this to completion
here pretty soon but uh
i noticed i've all i i've always been on
dissatisfied when somebody says well i
just don't trust you
right or i'm in a conversation with
somebody they talked about like
you know i don't trust this person all
right i don't trust that right
and i there's something about you right
there is something about when when
someone withdraws their trust from
something
there is this kind of blank because it's
almost like
almost nothing else could happen anymore
right
and i i uh
and i think i was working with some
clients or something like that
and they said something about well i
just don't trust them and i was like
well actually let's just say that you
can't let's just say
let's just pretend that you can't
um you can't not trust somebody
right let's just say that like
what you what if we say this is like so
you
what are you trusting in relationship
with them
right and it it took something like oh
yeah i
so it's like i trust my judgment that
they're not gonna
i trust that you're gonna hurt me i
trust an assessment of some kind that i
have
right and it's really interesting that
this sense in which
when you talk about not trusting someone
i've noticed this in relationships like
oh the book just stops nothing's
possible
right however i'm always in a trusting
relationship
with something in when i'm in
relationship with
with with somebody else and it may just
not be that i
trust you right or maybe i
or i more trust my assessment that
you're gonna betray me or
or whatever it is but there is a no
like and i i noticed in in those
conversations that something would break
open
right for that person like it just
became
it just didn't it stopped being just a
blank
impossibility and something became
possible
with this sense of like that that you
can't not
trust right you just you
you invest your trust into things you
can't like
not trust you just
you're trusting something right
and i think what you're i think what i'm
getting in this conversation
is is actually i think what i'm getting
is
an experience that i've been having and
i've never quite
thought about it in terms of or seen
quite that it
that it really is about investing
investing trust in something very very
deep
like the world right in it with a
certain
with a certain proactive
unconditionality
right
yeah really good to get getting to know
you thank you
thank you for this thank you as well it
was
a very very good conversation i think
absolutely
really like to appreciate your um
your i like that i like the sense
like when you go
and you it and then you lean forward
you're grappling with stuff i just that
it animates something that i'm sure i'm
gonna get
i'm sure i'm gonna continually hopefully
understand more about you but there's a
there's an earnestness
and a a sense of humor i sense
and it in a in it
an unbelievable unrelenting
hunger for all this
that we've been talking about
thank you that's my those are my
projections
the humor comes from the austrian like
just just austin
like usually the germans are you know
they are the the
kind of like the stiff people they like
order
but the austrians are more like it's the
relaxed
flow to everything there's music you
know yeah
great alright so let's do this again
great all right
bye